<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The shepherds starre now of late seene, and at this hower to be obserued merueilous orient in the East: which bringeth glad tydings to all that may behold her brightnes, hauing the foure elements with the foure capitall vertues in her, which makes her elementall and a vanquishor of all earthly humors. Described by a gentleman late of the right worthie and honorable the Lord Burgh, his companie &amp; retinue in the Briell in North-holland.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, Thomas, fl. 1591.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108276</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843939</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843939</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 523:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The shepherds starre now of late seene, and at this hower to be obserued merueilous orient in the East: which bringeth glad tydings to all that may behold her brightnes, hauing the foure elements with the foure capitall vertues in her, which makes her elementall and a vanquishor of all earthly humors. Described by a gentleman late of the right worthie and honorable the Lord Burgh, his companie &amp; retinue in the Briell in North-holland.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, Thomas, fl. 1591.</author>
                  <author>Theocritus. aut</author>
                  <author>Bradshaw, Alexander, fl. 1591.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Robinson, for William Iones, and are to be sould at his shop neere Holborne Condit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A gentleman late of the right worthie and honorable the Lord Burgh .." = Thomas Bradshaw.</note>
                  <note>Edited by Alexander Bradshaw.--STC.</note>
                  <note>A paraphrase upon the third of the Canticles of Theocritus.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The shepheards starre.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴ A²  B-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:1"/>
            <p>The Shepherds Starre, Now of late ſeene, and <hi>at this hower to be obſerued merueilous orient</hi> in the Eaſt: which bringeth glad tydings to all that may behold her brightnes, hauing <hi>the foure elements with the foure Capitall</hi> vertures in her, which makes her Elementall and a vanquiſhor of all earthly humors.</p>
            <p>Deſcribed by a Gentleman late of the Right worthie and honorable the Lord <hi>Burgh,</hi> his companie &amp; retinue in the <hi>Briell</hi> in North-holland.</p>
            <q>Tu ſihic eſſes aliter ſenties. <bibl>
                  <hi>Terent.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Amor fa molto: Argento fa touto.</p>
            <p>Printed by Robert Robinſon, for <hi>William</hi> Iones, and are to be ſould at his ſhop neere Holborne Condit. 159<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE RIGHT Honorables, &amp; puiſſant Barons, <hi>Robert Deuorex</hi> Earle of Eſſex, Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter, great Maſter of <hi>the Horſe for her Highnes: And vnto Thomas Lord</hi> Burgh, Baron of Gayns-burgh, Lord Gouernour of the towne of Bryell, and the Fortes of Newmanton, &amp; Cleyborow in North-Holland for her Maieſtie: health, &amp; increaſe of honour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue read, I take it, right honorables, of <hi>Polycletus</hi> rule:<note place="margin">Polyclet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Regula.</note> A ſpeeche applyed to thoſe men, whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie many haue imitated, more haue enuied, but none haue attained. Thoſe that haue imitated, haue been <hi>Socordes,</hi> and ſo vnworthie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neuer trauailed to knowe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:8706:3"/> of eſtate. Thoſe that haue enuied, haue beene <hi>Vecordes</hi> baſe conceipts, and ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing becauſe vnworthie. And thoſe that haue not attained, are <hi>Excordes</hi> in puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and infirmitie of the mind. But there are yet another number <hi>Cordati Homines</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed men for wiſedome, yet are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed for wealth. Theſe enuie not any mans eſtate, but attribute vnto Fortune, the goods of Fortune: To the bodie, the goods of the bodie: to the minde, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the minde: and to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> all things due vnto him. Such ſhould wiſe men be, that what they are not thought worthie of by the worthieſt; they ſhould content them ſelues with, as well as the meaneſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I conſidering, that I cannot atchieue the knowledge which is worthie of your moſt honorable fauours, requeſt, this may be worthie of your pacience. Wine which in baſe Dutch is called <hi>Drozen</hi> or <hi>Moder,</hi> is good for ſomewhat, it will make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound. So my wit may hereafter with your
<pb facs="tcp:8706:3"/> preſent protections &amp; honourable allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance make a ſimple. But as there is of the yeare foure quarters: ſo is there of a mans knowledge, fouretimes. The Spring: the Summer: the Autumne: and Winter. The infancie, the youth: the middle age, (ripe iudgement:) and the olde age (right follie.) And becauſe my knowledge is none, it cannot be termed any. Howbeit, for that I haue euer heard, my true honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lord and maiſter, publiſh your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips excellent partes, which he recordeth often from his heart: I doe the rather preſume of your Lordſhips clemencie in his abſence. That I may approach with all this ſimplicitie vnto all that ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Who in witt beeing a Paterne to all men: may (where it wanteth) be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone to mee. I cannot be tedious in my writing. Woulde I had the like priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, not to be odious in my enditing. But ſo had I neede to bee in Arte <hi>Polycle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> in happe <hi>Polycrates:</hi> which becauſe I
<pb facs="tcp:8706:4"/> am not, I care not. Onely, I reſpect your Lordſhips true eſtimation, and I expect the Readers due conſideration. I ceaſe, not ceaſing to remember your Lordſhips in my dayly wiſh for your long proſperitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honorable lordſhips bounden, and ſeruaunt to commaund: <hi>Thomas Bradſhaw.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:4"/>
            <head>To my well beloued brother, health and increaſe of knowledge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rother, I haue made bolde to publiſh the booke which you left me to my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate vſe. I was moued thereunto by your friends, and my fauourets heere in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. The matter is adiudged by ſome of learning, not to be vnworthie of the light. I meane not that light which you meant, when you gaue it mee to commit it to Vulcane. But I haue ſaued it, and it ſhall ſaue you: if not from vniuſt vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of backbyting wordes: yet from iuſt occaſion of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thoughtes. Manie will ſay, that an Engliſh booke of loue, is like a Marchpane, of which one may ſoone ſcale the walles, and leap into the Caſtle: for there is no foode in it to ſtay a hungrie ſtomack, nor ſubſtance in pleaſures to peruſe a learned Cenſure. Tis true, the argument of fond loue is feeble: becauſe the ſubiect of the matter is but an abiect. And the Genus of the thing will decay, where the ſpecies is onely faire without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther qualities. But your ſcope is ſuch you aime at, that you could not ſpeake leſſe of it, nor well ſay more. Sith the manner was as truely inacted, as the matter is duely reported. And ſeeing in al demaunds, there is but foure things to be knowen, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. You may eaſily reſolue any one that ſhall carpe, with all theſe foure: For the ſtrictnes of the intention, ſhall excuſe the dulnes of the inuention. So I commit you to your delightes of thoſe colde countries. From the Court at Greenewich, vpon Saint Georges day 1591 Aprill. 23.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your brother to commaund: <hi>Alexander Bradſhaw.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:5"/>
            <head>I. M. Eſquier, his farewell to England and to the Author.</head>
            <l>SIth the time and tyde with instance,</l>
            <l>And their ſtately troopes of ſailing,</l>
            <l>Must conuey my ſweete remembrance,</l>
            <l>And my ſelfe, my ſelfe bewayling.</l>
            <l>Why ſhould Thyrſtie thoughts induring,</l>
            <l>Not be quencht with weeping moyſture,</l>
            <l>Why ſhould ſhee ſhould ſhee alluring,</l>
            <l>Walke in me as in a Cloyſture,</l>
            <l>Let hope ſell away her helping,</l>
            <l>For helpe ſends away her maiſter,</l>
            <l>Sith hope and help both inuenting,</l>
            <l>Findes for loues ſore no ſweet plaſter.</l>
            <l>Farewell natiue ſoyle and ſubſtance:</l>
            <l>Farewell loue in preſence panting:</l>
            <l>Beautie, you whoſe large allowance</l>
            <l>Made me not remember wanting.</l>
            <l>Farewell all delight of Courting:</l>
            <l>Farewell pretie booke my treaſure.</l>
            <l>Farewell Fairie Nymphes exhorting,</l>
            <l>Idle heads to die in pleaſure.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Quod natura negat, reddere nemo poteſt.</l>
                  <l>Quod natura dedit, tollere nemo poteſt.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Authors farewell to England, and</hi> to his moſt intier friend I. M. Eſquyer.</head>
            <l>THe growing hatred of my deadly foe,</l>
            <l>Which groning lamentation would forgo:</l>
            <l>Doth more inforce me when I weep &amp; waile,</l>
            <l>As doth the roaring wind the raging ſaile.</l>
            <l>And as the tempeſt is increaſt with raine:</l>
            <l>So watrie teares my dririe cares maintaine.</l>
            <l>The ſprowts of yong inuention limber ſhake,</l>
            <l>Like Willowes made by calmeſt gale to quake.</l>
            <l>Miſtres Experience, youthfull wittes ſhee rypes:</l>
            <l>But all her knowledge coſteth pinching ſtrypes.</l>
            <l>Ioue all my labours bringeth vnto nought:</l>
            <l>For that againſt his will my wit hath wrought.</l>
            <l>Wit learne to will, not by ſiniſter driftes:</l>
            <l>Wit learne to will, not by thy priuie ſhiftes.</l>
            <l>Learne wit to will, not by vnlawfull helpes:</l>
            <l>Learne wit that will is one of Careleſſe whelps.</l>
            <l>And as a thing vntimely brought to light:</l>
            <l>Which being blind, is fitteſt for the night.</l>
            <l>For when in ſecret bed like graue I lye,</l>
            <l>Thoughts apteſt are vnfitteſt things to ſpye.</l>
            <l>Wit learne to will all things encounter will:</l>
            <l>Wit learne to will thy baſe intents to kill.</l>
            <l>Learne wit to will no more wealth by deceit,</l>
            <l>Leſt wit &amp; will be caught with beggers beight.</l>
            <l>Tall Cedars, Pyne trees, &amp; aſpiring ſtates,</l>
            <l>Haue humble ſhrubs &amp; valleis to their mates.</l>
            <l>When whirling winde on high things taketh hold:</l>
            <l>Then in the vale is leſſer blaſt of cold.</l>
            <l>The meane betwixt both high and lowe is beſt:</l>
            <l>Therein the Author ſetteth vp his reſt.</l>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, De Coelo deſcendit.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:6"/>
            <head>T. G. Eſquier, his replye to the farewell of the Author.</head>
            <l>SIth that wiſedome is diuine:</l>
            <l>Wit to wiſedome muſt reſigne.</l>
            <l>For though wit doth dwell on earth,</l>
            <l>Wiſedome hath immortall birth.</l>
            <l>Wittie men &amp; no wiſe minde,</l>
            <l>Are ſuger ſweet new refinde.</l>
            <l>Which for tast doth beare the bell:</l>
            <l>Yet doth wast before it ſell:</l>
            <l>So doth wit make a shewe</l>
            <l>Like goodſhewers, but is a dewe:</l>
            <l>A dewe, which ſtill doth diſplay,</l>
            <l>Wiſedome like a Summer day.</l>
            <l>For both they one to the other,</l>
            <l>Dearer are then any brother:</l>
            <l>Deare ſo deare, as when a child</l>
            <l>Thou in <hi>Pallas</hi> lap haſt ſmyld.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pallas</hi> boſome, <hi>Pallas</hi> armes,</l>
            <l>muſt shrowd, muſt ſaue thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harms.</l>
            <l>Baſe inuentions vilde annoy,</l>
            <l>Still intending ending ioy:</l>
            <l>That <hi>Euphues</hi> is neuer good,</l>
            <l>Which weareth Had Jwisthis hood.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Dictum puta, <hi>Thomas Groos.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:6"/>
            <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, I knowe no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to mooue mee to write vnto you, ſith I cannot remoue you from your preiudiciall opinion. It is peculiar to euerie one, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of a booke ſo ſingular, as that no moſt exquiſit worke can ſatisfie the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt expectation in his deſire of reading. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie reaſon is, becauſe euerie Readers emulous and couetous minde, hopeth to finde once a booke made all by the figure <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Cicero 3. de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator. illuſtris ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>planatio rerum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que quaſigetan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſub aſpectum pene ſubiectio.</note> Aboue all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit: And ſo longeth to finde a writer, that can ſet downe his matter as well as his heart can thinke. This ſhall neuer be God wot. For, firſt the ſimple may, I confeſſe, be pleaſed ſooneſt with that which they vnderſtande leaſt, but admyre moſt. But what a fond pleaſing were this? Yet tis ſo. For <hi>Iris</hi> is fained to be <hi>Thaumantis filia.</hi> The Raynbowe is the daughter of Admiration. The coulours pleaſe much, becauſe they are little perceiued, and leaſt of all coulours knowen what they are. The Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond is onely rare, becauſe it deceiueth the eye with newe varietie, ſuch as the ſight is not ſtill ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of: Marke it when you will. For the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to pleaſe them, I will not preſume to ſpeake howe, becauſe I cannot. Onely this I proteſt: There is not a letter in this ſillie Pamphlet, that by my placing is ſet there, to diſpleaſe any one, or to
<pb facs="tcp:8706:7"/> pleaſe manie. Only this: Let the wiſeſt giue their verdicts, and the reſt holde their tongues. If I fall by the one, I wil be ſure for euer hereafter to ſtand by the other: and ſo diſpleaſe neither with any more Toyes. In haſt on Saint Georges day. <hi>Aprill.</hi> 23.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:8706:7"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Paraphraſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the third of the Canticles</hi> of Theocritus, Dialogue wiſe.</head>
            <stage>Amaryllis. Corydon. Tityrus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Orydon.</speaker>
               <p>The prime of bewtie may I preſume to tel you my lot?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amaryl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</speaker>
               <p>yes <hi>Corydon,</hi> ſo that your folly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſeeme to bee no greater then your fortune is, that being by generation a Shepherd, you clyme not by vſurpation from I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, to be God <hi>Pan</hi> in Arcadie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I am not <hi>Pan,</hi> for I haue not armes to ſhew: or if I haue, they are not faire and glittering like the ſunne beames viſible like the ſame which women giue.<note place="margin">The proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of God Pan the ſon of Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorgus an inchaunter.</note> Yet am I <hi>Pan</hi> for faire <hi>Amaryllis</hi> ſake, or I beare in my breaſt the loue lie ſtar <hi>Nebris,</hi> the very Image of your ſingelaritiy. And of my flocke, I learne to be laſciuious. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to make you merie, becauſe it is of me deitie alwaies to laugh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Well <hi>Corydon,</hi> tel mee your lot, &amp; I will be preiudicial vnto you, that you ſhal haue the ſhorteſt cut for your labour.<note place="margin">Crotona an auncient towne in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly on that ſide where Sicilia cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Trina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cria borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>There is a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome amongeſt vs Swaynes in <hi>Crotona</hi> to elect bie our <hi>Diuinatione</hi> Lordes &amp; Ladies, with the leafe of the flower <hi>Telephilon,</hi> which being laide before the fier leapeth vnto them whom it loueth &amp; ſkippeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them whom it hateth. <hi>Tityrus</hi> and I in experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:8706:8"/> of our lot whoſe happe it ſhould be to inioye your loue, inſteede of <hi>Telephilon</hi> we burned <hi>Miſtletoe</hi> and Boxe for our <hi>Diuination,</hi> &amp; vnto me <hi>Amaryllis</hi> you fled, &amp; choſe rather to turne to an vnworthy Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, then to burne like an vnworthy louer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie I am <hi>Corydon</hi> that the loue of fooles is apt to take hold, where there is no handle, and many times ſo quicke of conceipt is loue, that in ſteede of her own mate, ſhe conceiues with childe in the darke with a <hi>Niger,</hi> though ſhe neuer ſawe the man. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch euents are incident to the citizens of <hi>Crotona,</hi> when they are farre from it: I therefore do baniſh from my diſcretion all fonde loue, when I am neereſt vnto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>ô honorable <hi>Amaryllis</hi> it is not my inductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to perſwade you to vouchſafe to fauor baſe mortalitie as your equall, but to protect ſimple mankind as your ſeruant. For I knowe beeing a bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſtarre as you are, and walking no where but in the milkie way, you doe deſtinate as comets doe, the verie death of a prince for loue of you, rather then anie body ſhal inioy it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>No; you do exceed in your accounts, for I can loue much becauſe it is laudable, but not loue many, becauſe it is not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Not as of a good thing, the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is his that hath it, but the communication of it doth belong to all men; but as of a bad thing, ſuch as loue, which is a lewd toye, the poſſeſſion beeinge in a woman which cannot ſurrender, the communication muſt be but to one man, leſt the inheritor ſhould proue baſe, where the Landladie hath too many tenants.
<pb facs="tcp:8706:8"/> And ſo my diſcretion, bee farre wide of that you wiſhe it to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yet in the graueſt modeſtie there may be a ſmile, and on that is dead with ſound may chaunce to ſcral, &amp; once a yeer the drieſt Burr Oke will weepe vnto you, if you offer but to write the firſt letter of your name vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſtatelie breſt. Why may not then <hi>Amaryllis</hi> once a yeer vſe the like wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſh teares, to any that ſhall prefer their mindes to her ſtatelie conſideration?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo; for faithful loue is good in it ſelfe, and not reſpectiue good: for in it ſelfe, it doth conſider a ſympathie, which euer is betwixt two, and no more, according to a ground among the ſages: True-loue neuer buildeth her own neſt, but ſucceedeth the Turtle Doue in hers: and they are ſaide aboue all other birdes to haue teats and pappes, to nouriſh loues darlings in their neſt: wherein ſhee neuer, bringeth but two vnto light, and they are both copercioners of ech others vitall ſpirites, and not vnlike twins, vnto which one more admitted maketh lyke a monſter, from which one taken away, cauſeth preſent death. As they ſay <hi>Pythagoras</hi> writ for his firme to al his epiſtles: two in body, one in minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I hold it felicity for me to be borne onlie to heare you ſpeak, but more happie it were for me to die quickly if this be true, for then I ſee by the perſpectiue glaſſe of your angelical beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, how it is written in my forheade, that my heart dooth bleed for loue: yet if neither of vs ſtand in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and becauſe the gawdie day is come, &amp; the fellowſhip is granted to ſome noble perſonage that
<pb facs="tcp:8706:9"/> can ſhewe beſt friendes for it: then giue <hi>Corydon</hi> leaue to ſacrifice for his loſſe the ſimpleſt guift that may be, a handfull of lines, in eaſe of a world of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>You may do wel to writ, that with your wit you may write a way your care: no doubte but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Mars</hi> lefte you, if <hi>Neptune</hi> fauour you as he did <hi>Pelops,</hi> you may winne king <hi>Aenomaus</hi> daughter in warlike race: ſo comming home, if your hungrie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tantalus</hi> be aliue he may bake you in a pie, and bidde the gods to the banket for ioy of your depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this miſerable worlde: but beware leaſte <hi>Ceres</hi> be there at the feaſt, for ſhee will eate a whole ſhoulder of you for meere ſpite: becauſe ſhe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that you haue beene verie vnfaithfull to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men kinde. But if <hi>Mercurie</hi> loue you ſo wel as he did <hi>Pelops,</hi> and lend you an Ivorie ſhoulder to beare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a bobbe, and commaund <hi>Clotho</hi> to call you to life againe, then come to me and I will ſay more to your matter of loue, till then I praye you giue mee leaue to chuſe whether I will loue you or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Some women thinke it is as martiall a victory with their tongues to ouercome &amp; win the wiſp, as we ſhepheards with our pipes to win the garland. But in al the dialogues wher ſhepherds vſe to ſpeak, note that he which ſpeaketh laſt ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth moſt. Would I might ſay no more but <hi>Vici</hi> (as none may ſaie) not <hi>Veni, vidi,</hi> as all may ſaie, or <hi>Veni, vidi, vici,</hi> as <hi>Caeſar</hi> and thoſe which are more worthie of your preſence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>And would I cold conquer <hi>Caeſar</hi> with words as he won ſome nations without deeds then I proteſt <hi>Corydon</hi> ſhould feede my ſheepe on the
<pb facs="tcp:8706:9"/> mountaines, and <hi>Tityrus</hi> my goates on the rocks, but vnto my preſence, no ſuch vulgare creepinge wormes ſhould approch; no not to my ſolitary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Content you faire ladie albeit you are the pride of euerie braunche, it ſtandeth with your humility &amp; honor, to entertaine ſeruice ſometimes vnto your perſon: leaſt forgetting what you are, you remember what you ſhould not, and ſo alwaies v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to walke in the aire, you forget to walke aright vpon the earth: &amp; for want of the true vſe of your ſelfe, you maie ſoone fall. For all thinges that are of great ſubſtance do decline down-ward, &amp; the light things are lifted vpwarde: ſo you maie catche that foule fall on the backe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tityrus</hi> counſell is good, though ſomewhat ſwiniſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>And ſo is not your talk becauſe it is more then ſwaniſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You are not to be angry when you are giltles, for that is not the intire property of a courtier, but rather the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Neither are ſhepherds to prate but of goates &amp; lambes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>So we do of the lambes of <hi>Venus,</hi> which cauſe the ſons of carefull parentes to come home once a yeere for their ſins, with the prodigall, when they haue eaten acornes for their miſtris ſake ſeuen long yeers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Come <hi>Tityrus,</hi> let vs ſing for <hi>Amaryllis</hi> ſake, &amp; contend for her, ſith wee can not haue her giuen vnto mee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Then if I ſing beſt, king <hi>Midas</hi> ſhall iudge for me, becauſe her dignitie ought not to be cenſured by one no worthie then our ſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Doe ſo, and if hee iudge for either of you I will beſtowe a greene Veluet hoode on him, to hide his Aſſes eares: and on you both my iollie Shepheards
<pb facs="tcp:8706:10"/> two Oten pipes that you may conuoye vnto his eares, ſuch melody as is moſt fit for his merite. <hi>R. M.A.H.A.As.</hi> But begin your plaine ſong.</p>
            </sp>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
               <body>
                  <head>Corydon and Tityrus contention.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                     <l>In a time of merrie ſporte,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Amaryllis</hi> did reſorte,</l>
                     <l>With her gratious louing lookes</l>
                     <l>To the Chryſtall running brookes:</l>
                     <l>Where I <hi>Corydon</hi> did dwel,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Corydon</hi> the sheapheardes ſpell:</l>
                     <l>For to ſhepheardes doth belong,</l>
                     <l>All the pride of wanton ſong.</l>
                     <l>There to <hi>Amaryllis</hi> viewe,</l>
                     <l>Shepheard ſent his homage dwe:</l>
                     <l>Such a ſeruice as of right,</l>
                     <l>Came to ſhort of ſuch a wight.</l>
                     <l>For I ſent my thoughtes vnfit,</l>
                     <l>To admire at ſuch a wit:</l>
                     <l>And I ſent my daſeling eyes,</l>
                     <l>To behold the Empire skies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
                     <l>Shepheard leaue thy fonde conceite,</l>
                     <l>For her beautie prooues a beyte:</l>
                     <l>To beguyle the craftiſt eies,</l>
                     <l>That in court doe skale the skies.</l>
                     <l>Like as fiſhes ſaye to flee,</l>
                     <l>When dame <hi>Venus</hi> ſtar they ſee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſweete <hi>Amaryllis</hi> face,</l>
                     <l>Giues my muſe a ſower diſgrace:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8706:10"/>
                     <l>Drownds in Lethe al my arte,</l>
                     <l>Setteth at her heele my ſmarte:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tityrus</hi> my fellowe ſwaine,</l>
                     <l>Seekes her heauenly lookes to gaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis our tender Lambes haue part,</l>
                     <l>Of the ioyes of her ſweete hart:</l>
                     <l>They as ſhe, and ſhe as they,</l>
                     <l>Innocentes faire lookes bewray.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Amaryllis</hi> whiles we striue,</l>
                     <l>Keepes our tender flockes aliue:</l>
                     <l>For our flockes well kept doo prooue,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe cares not for our loue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
                     <l>Hapleſſe wee, and happie ſhee:</l>
                     <l>Of all that dwell in Italie.</l>
                  </sp>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
               <body>
                  <head>Corydons contention.</head>
                  <l>In <hi>Crotona Sicill</hi> mount,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amaryllis</hi> Paramount,</l>
                  <l>Liues and loues no worldlie fame,</l>
                  <l>Loues of life to keepe her name.</l>
                  <l>He that dooth approch her grace,</l>
                  <l>Must appeare an Angels face:</l>
                  <l>For her preſence will appale,</l>
                  <l>Him that beſt can tell his tale.</l>
                  <l>Whiſpering lips, like nets, which call,</l>
                  <l>Heauenly quailes to be her thrall:</l>
                  <l>Sweet notes liking to inſpier,</l>
                  <l>Like, but not like, <hi>Syrens</hi> hier.</l>
                  <l>Such a voice as dooth inchante,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8706:11"/>
                  <l>Nightingals her walks to haunt.</l>
                  <l>In both cheekes her ruddy type,</l>
                  <l>Makes them ſing of cherries ripe:</l>
                  <l>Then like <hi>Ecco</hi> ſhe dooth vſe</l>
                  <l>Notes, which makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtay &amp; muſe.</l>
                  <l>Notes which from the hearers eye,</l>
                  <l>Make drops fall as from the skie:</l>
                  <l>Notes which through her ſtraunge right eye,</l>
                  <l>Send forth pictures of the skie.</l>
                  <l>Which eie when it dooth aſcende,</l>
                  <l>Then behold I ſee my ende:</l>
                  <l>For no tongue can then relate,</l>
                  <l>How ſun-beames loue thoughtes amate:</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Apelles by whom only Princes were pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red began Amaryllis ſo exquiſite that he cold not finiſh, becauſe he could not conceiue her perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where vpon he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred Venus pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture far vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryllis.</note>
                     <hi>Apelles</hi> did miſſe to applie,</l>
                  <l>In her picture this right eie.</l>
                  <l>Where vpon ſome do coniect,</l>
                  <l>By that ſhadowe imperfect:</l>
                  <l>He meant <hi>Amaryllis</hi> ſhape,</l>
                  <l>And that <hi>Venus</hi> was her ape.</l>
                  <l>Then did <hi>Zeuxis</hi> frame her ſhape,</l>
                  <l>In her brest a bunch of grape:</l>
                  <l>For loue whereof in her ſweete breſt,</l>
                  <l>Nightingales do make their neſt:</l>
                  <l>As tame fowles ſo they afforde,</l>
                  <l>All the yeare birdes to recorde:</l>
                  <l>And in the merrie month of May,</l>
                  <l>Nightingales for night and day.</l>
                  <l>In the ſequel of the yeere,</l>
                  <l>To her voice their burden beare:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8706:11"/>
                  <l>In the Quire of her heart,<note place="margin">Amphion whoſe eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce tames wilde Satyres, he was the firſt inuentors of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rules <hi>Amphion</hi> with his art:</l>
                  <l>Which makes me vnciuil ſwaine</l>
                  <l>her perfections to maintaine.</l>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
               <body>
                  <head>Amaryllis reanſwer to the Shepherds contention.</head>
                  <l>Iollie Shepherds, no fond prayſe</l>
                  <l>is of force my mind to raiſe:</l>
                  <l>If I had Adonis heare,</l>
                  <l>which the purple Roſe doth weare:</l>
                  <l>If I had <hi>Dianas</hi> grace,</l>
                  <l>If I had dame <hi>Venus</hi> face,</l>
                  <l>If I were king <hi>Titans</hi> child,</l>
                  <l>namde <hi>Aurora</hi> faire and milde,</l>
                  <l>Beautie, birth, Grace purpurred,</l>
                  <l>holds no ſoule from fatall bed.</l>
                  <l>Wiſedome, wit, and knowledge hid</l>
                  <l>Seruants are to <hi>Clothos</hi> thrid.</l>
                  <l>The true vſe of harmonie,<note place="margin">The auncient Graecians were vſed to ſalute their children into the world with teares, and to laugh at their domes day. Lucretia of Rome that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled Sextus Tarquinius al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is to waile our miſerie:</l>
                  <l>Twas inuented to take place</l>
                  <l>at our death &amp; happie caſe:</l>
                  <l>At our birth a ſadder vaine</l>
                  <l>was ſtill vſde to ſhew our paine.</l>
                  <l>If I haue <hi>Lucretias</hi> gift,</l>
                  <l>to diſcerne <hi>Tarquinius</hi> drift:</l>
                  <l>And obey chaſt <hi>Veſtas</hi> call,</l>
                  <l>and beware by others fall:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8706:12"/>
                  <l>Sweet voice, faire lookes, &amp; chaſt life,</l>
                  <l>are large portions with a wife.</l>
                  <l>And the Iewels virgins weare,</l>
                  <l>Is good fame hangde at their eare.</l>
                  <l>We by this may riſe withall,</l>
                  <l>Riſing well may neuer fall.</l>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Can there proceed from Nature more giftes, or of nurture more rewardes then <hi>Amaryllis</hi> inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? not to her ſelfe inioyeth, but doth to her frinds participate, vertues for their learning &amp; examples for their liuing. And ſurely <hi>Tityrus</hi> tis in vaine that we ſollicit her with vaine loue, for they whoſe ſage wittes are inhabited with ſuch relations, cannot be at leaſure to <hi>Cupids</hi> inuentions,<note place="margin">
                     <p>For the Cock is moſt proue to Cupide.</p>
                     <p>For the Parrat is moſt prompt to ſpeake.</p>
                  </note> the which ſecure conceipt hath firſt ingendred of the braine of a Cocke, as they faine, that wiſedome ſprang firſt of the braine of Parrat, which was the firſt <hi>Iuppiter</hi> that euer ſpake: And ſo <hi>Mynerua</hi> was as much a kinne to a Parrat as <hi>Venus</hi> to a Cocke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>True, verie true. But I ſee ſhee is elected by <hi>Veſta</hi> to bee Veſtall, and hath either ſworne Chaſtitie, or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie ſworne her. Yet becauſe in mouing of her, wee cannot remoue her from her true eſtimation of honour, wee will heare her and ſee her and ſaye the beſt, for of leſt medling with her beautie we ſhal ſooneſt get her bountie: And of moſt praiſing of her, wee ſhall (to her repute) moſt flatter her. For if ſhe would admit titles and vaine appellation, then ſhee would of her ſelfe ſoone haue high eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and ſo be <hi>Philautos.</hi> As on the contrarie, if
<pb facs="tcp:8706:12"/> ſhee would endure fugillation, then had ſhee of her ſelfe a baſe eſtimation.<note place="margin">
                     <p>Plutar. de Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione.</p>
                     <p>Quae ſe plus iuſto amat qualis eſt vide Ariſtot li 2 mag moral. cap 13. &amp;. 14.</p>
                  </note> To this end <hi>Plutarch</hi> notes that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. They that are inamorde of them ſelues, are at leaſure to be flattered by others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>I will aſſay her grauely againe with ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie newes, to which in honeſt recreation ſhee hath euer enclined: yet therein from preciſeſt vertue ſhee hath neuer declined. You knowe <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> in <hi>Virgill</hi> there was ſometimes a famous learned man of our trade of ſhepherding, who was alſo a famous learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his own trade of theeuing, who after manie theeuiſh exploits, at the laſt ſtole away great <hi>Hercules</hi> faire herd: which he brought from <hi>Geryon</hi> the tyrant of <hi>Spaine,</hi> brother to the <hi>Philip</hi> which v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpeth thoſe dominions. This <hi>Cacus</hi> miſtruſting leaſt the tracke of the beaſtes would be purſued by worthie <hi>Hercules,</hi> drewe them all backeward by the tailes into his caue. <hi>Hercules</hi> freſhſuing his herd, &amp; ſeeing no print of a foote toward the denne, but all fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ward, was perſwaded as the craftieſt Fox in all <hi>Aeſope</hi> wold haue bin, if in reuiewing the Lyons den he had but ſeen the like ſteps: and haue thought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then any harme in <hi>Cacus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Hercules &amp; Simia</p>
                     <p>Craft againſt Force doth litle auaile.</p>
                     <p>Camelus &amp; For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mica.</p>
                  </note> Preſently after driuing the reſt of his herd by the wales of the caue, they chanced to low: (&amp; as all creatures know their own call) ſo theſe ſtolen cattel did bellow vnto their fellowes, which the noble perſonage hearing, brake the dore of the caue, &amp; the necke of the theefe, and ſo had his faire flocke againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amar.</speaker>
               <p>Too faire a death for ſo foule a fact.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8706:13"/>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>We heare in <hi>Italie</hi> that there is now as cruell a <hi>Philip</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> as there was a <hi>Geryon</hi> then, and as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed a <hi>Hercules</hi> in <hi>Fraunce</hi> nowe, as euer there was king of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> This Spaniſh tyrant hath many <hi>Cacus</hi> of his league &amp; nation, which ſeeke to ſteale away that faire herd all of milke whit cattel, which <hi>Hercules</hi> and his friend preſerue for breede. The <hi>Cacuſes</hi> do practiſe by pollicie to drawe them defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medly into their vgglie caues, but the <hi>Herculeians</hi> indeuour to preſerue ſuch beautifull breed for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and to ſerue holie vſes. The <hi>Cacuſes</hi> haue often committed this pillage vpon all the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour kings herdes that inhabite thereabout. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire therefore of thee my <hi>Tityrus,</hi> who haſt often heard of this action, whie the <hi>Herculeians</hi> do not preſently inuade ſome of their vſurpations &amp; gaine the patronage to themſelues: for of all trials ſpeede is the ſcope &amp; felicitie, and that which is the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite of all hope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>This I thinke the firſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that <hi>Hercules</hi> muſt achieue, is to ſee the death of the monſtrous Lyon in the wood <hi>Nemea,</hi> which can neither be ſlaine by metall nor ſtone: then may they more eaſily aſpire to that which is the effect of the firſt labour. And the firſt wil be the cauſe of the ſecond.<note place="margin">Ierome of the twelue labors of Hercules, writeth to this effect on the 10 chap. of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</note> So that <hi>Hydra</hi> in <hi>lerna malorum</hi> may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily victord: <hi>Si Leoni vulpem adiungas. Hydra</hi> is the ſecond labour of the <hi>Herculeians</hi> which daily they do victor: albeit an hundred heads ſucceed vppon the necke of that monſter ſo ſoon as he is behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: yet at laſt when nature ſhall extinguiſh that
<pb facs="tcp:8706:13"/> monſter, ſich Arte cannot ſink him, (when that is done, if it be yet vndone:) Then I aſſure my ſelf, that <hi>Hercules</hi> in <hi>France</hi> ſhal haue ſuch ſucceſſe, as that he neede not neither for publique honour nor for priuat weale, vndertake any more of the twelue labours, the one being a worke of pollicie, the other of proweſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Then <hi>Amaryllis</hi> honor you ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with your chaſtitie of life, that when you haue all things belonging to preſent eſtate, you want not that litle <hi>Atomus</hi> the ſoule (which other women they ſay want) which of your future and celeſtiall eſtate muſt be the forerunner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>For your counſell Shepheard I render you gracious lookes, the rather for that your theame tendes not vnto graceleſſe loue. My religion I account the right of my countrie, and the inheritage vſually of them which haue none other lands. Euery one may be an heire (as in Gauelkind) to ſincere religion, in which the yongeſt hath a title as well as the eldeſt. And therefore we learne that worthie men haue carried the burden of their countrie Gods, in the middeſt of any ſpoiles vpon their backes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: amongeſt whome <hi>Aeneas</hi> the founder of our natiue ſoyle is canonized,<note place="margin">Ea eſt falſae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis nota cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Plato.</note> not ſo much for conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his parents in ſafetie from the ſacking of <hi>Troy,</hi> as for that he preſerued his countrie gods, knowing it to be a falſe Religion, to haue ſought newe gods elſewhere for money or rewardes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Then do I marueile <hi>Amaryllis</hi> at one thing greatly: I haue often heard you alledge as an aucthoritie of a wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:8706:14"/> Senatour in our land, who vſed to pronounce, that of the two Religions, there is but one end and that the one is but a little the farther way about, both may come to one home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>I haue by heare-ſay ſo been informed, but eſteeme no trueth but one, neither loue I that <hi>Ianus</hi> ſhould mock me in my iourney; and when I were faire for it, ſhould ſtand in ſome place of doubtfull way, with two faces vnder one hood, &amp; point both waies: ſo that I may miſtake him, and go the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt way about: I may ſo be wearie of my life, if the way be a purging &amp; faintie hoat way, before I come to my iourneys ende. I haue heard of two Ladies which often are placed in the way where all <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leians</hi> walke: the one ladie <hi>Voluptuous,</hi> the other ladie <hi>Vertue:</hi> and that the pleſurable ladie hath the more efficient perſwaſions to induce trauellers to their deſtruction, then ladie Vertue hath to reduce them to their ſaluation: That her way is faire and broad, and promiſeth more aſſurance of reſt then ladie Vertue doth: whoſe pathes are vnpleaſant, whoſe waies tedious, but in the end, there is a Paradiſe of moſt daintie deuiſes, which <hi>Corydon</hi> you knowe is moſt fit for Ladies, and moſt fauoured of mee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Good reaſon <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> that you ſhould fauour the ſoules health aboue the bodies, and things to come rather then pleaſant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipts which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent deceites. The Dialogue I haue conuerted for your vſe out of his proper language in the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memorables of <hi>Xenophon.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="dialogue">
                  <body>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8706:14"/>
                     <head>A Dialogue betwixt Hercules and the two Ladies, Volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and Vertuous. Xenophon. li. 2. Memorabilium.</head>
                     <l>As I wandred all alone,</l>
                     <l>In theſe greenewoods Sommers clothing,</l>
                     <l>To my ſelfe I made my mone,</l>
                     <l>Why I had my life in loathing.</l>
                     <l>At the laſt the carefull aire</l>
                     <l>Did conuey my cauſe of mourning</l>
                     <l>To theſe Ladies paſsing faire,</l>
                     <l>Who well knew my inward burning.</l>
                     <l>To whome when I vaild my Crest,</l>
                     <l>Vailde my Armes before their preſence,</l>
                     <l>And beheld lawne apornes prest,</l>
                     <l>Pure like Altars for my Incenſe,</l>
                     <l>Then I ceaſt not to recall,</l>
                     <l>Hilles, woods, groues, trees, dales, al wandring,</l>
                     <l>Which accompanied my thrall,</l>
                     <l>Wordes, nor deeds, nor comfort rendring.</l>
                     <l>When theſe Ladies had ageſſe</l>
                     <l>Who I was that ſo did trauell,</l>
                     <l>Did their ſacred termes addreſſe,</l>
                     <l>To conuey mee from my perill.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Voluptas.</speaker>
                        <l>Firſt dame Pleaſure did preſume,</l>
                        <l>Shining brightly not by Nature,</l>
                        <l>Shinde cares like clowdes to conſume,</l>
                        <l>With the blaſing of her feature.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8706:15"/>
                        <l>And her eies were open wide,</l>
                        <l>That ſhee quickly might intangle,</l>
                        <l>Moſt vaine lookes which catch at pride,</l>
                        <l>As the fiſh doth at the Angle.</l>
                        <l>And her garments in like ſort</l>
                        <l>were as wide and worne wide open:</l>
                        <l>Entertaining bold reſort,</l>
                        <l>Knew her ſhop without a token.</l>
                        <l>But I muſing at her gate,</l>
                        <l>Marueiled at no ſuch wunder,</l>
                        <l>As to ſee her ſhadowes ſtate,</l>
                        <l>And her ſelfe to ſtand a ſunder.</l>
                        <l>For I thought no Atomie</l>
                        <l>To be of ſo ſmall acquaintance,</l>
                        <l>As to want her companie,</l>
                        <l>Or to ſeeke her lewd alliance.</l>
                        <l>Shee began to make report</l>
                        <l>Of the youthes of her profeſſion,</l>
                        <l>Which ſhee cald a ſweete conſort</l>
                        <l>Of fine wittes without diſcretion.</l>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Thoſe that loue mee call mee <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, Thoſe that hate mee, call mee <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, Felicitie. Igna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>e.</note>Then I knowing what ſhee would,</l>
                        <l>For ſhee cald her ſelfe, Dame Pleaſure:</l>
                        <l>Told her that I would be bold</l>
                        <l>To go ſeeke a richer a treaſure.</l>
                        <l>Of loue, deſire, luſt, ſweete wordes,</l>
                        <l>To my eies, eares, taſt, &amp; ſpeaking:</l>
                        <l>There appeard with ſhrill records,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Helens</hi> Eunuke Nectar eating.</l>
                        <l>All which pleaſures without paines</l>
                        <l>Shee commended to my fauour:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8706:15"/>
                        <l>But I did reſigne the gaines.</l>
                        <l>Which comes of too ſweet a ſauour.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>tus.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <l>Then vertue faire of her ſelfe,</l>
                        <l>Did informe my ſimple meaning,</l>
                        <l>What was pleaſures idle pelfe,</l>
                        <l>Not to ſowe but liue by gleaning:</l>
                        <l>She began in weeping wiſe,</l>
                        <l>To intreate my tender nonage,</l>
                        <l>To beware by her aduiſe,</l>
                        <l>Of faire lookes the gate of bondage.</l>
                        <l>Tis not pleaſure bringeth reſt,</l>
                        <l>No man makes the gods his fautors</l>
                        <l>By delighte or pleaſant ieſt,</l>
                        <l>Of the which they are not autors.</l>
                        <l>Tis deſert that dooth preſent,</l>
                        <l>Euerie labor to his hire:</l>
                        <l>Pleaſant wits doe oft inuent,</l>
                        <l>Perfect art dooth ſtill aſpire.</l>
                        <l>Doe but marke good naturd ground,</l>
                        <l>How it dooth reward the ſower:</l>
                        <l>Doe but marke good naturd ſound,</l>
                        <l>For one touch it yeeldeth fower.</l>
                        <l>Seelie ſheepe that yeeld you cloth,</l>
                        <l>Muſt be waſhed in due ſeaſon:</l>
                        <l>Lazie kine are verie loth,</l>
                        <l>To yeeld you milke without ſome reaſon.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hercules</hi> is borne to wars,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe that honour ſuch a calling,</l>
                        <l>Muſt not ſit and gape at ſtars,</l>
                        <l>Till they ſee their foes a falling.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8706:16"/>
                        <l>If in boyſtrous warres at length,</l>
                        <l>Thou incurre ſome rare distreſſe,</l>
                        <l>Vertues Reſcue with thy ſtrength,</l>
                        <l>Shall bring deſprate care redreſſe.</l>
                        <l>If thou wouldeſt preuaile in force,</l>
                        <l>Know that exerciſe confirming,</l>
                        <l>Is to ſtrength a better courſe,</l>
                        <l>Then the bookes of Pleaſures learning.</l>
                        <l>Farewell noble <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of all warlike prowes the Engine,</l>
                        <l>Let no wandring Knightes diſtreſſe</l>
                        <l>Force thoughts baſe ſhifts to imagine.</l>
                        <l>Then I ſong loth to depart,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Voluptas.</speaker>
                        <l>Then dame Pleaſure red this leaſon,</l>
                        <l>That this painfull ſchoole of Arte,</l>
                        <l>And dame Vertues pathes are geaſon.</l>
                        <l>I reanſwerd to my skill,</l>
                        <l>This is all your pleaſures fulneſſe:</l>
                        <l>That the bellie you may fill,</l>
                        <l>Though the bodie liue in dulneſſe.</l>
                        <l>And thoſe falſe Ioyes you may waſh,</l>
                        <l>With fierce <hi>Bacchus</hi> which is luſtie,</l>
                        <l>To deceiue the ſillie paſsh,</l>
                        <l>To be drunke not being thirstie.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8706:16"/>
               <speaker>Corydon.</speaker>
               <p>I ioy <hi>Amaryllis</hi> to ſee a fable ſo to agree with truth. They ſay, into the <hi>Elyzean</hi> fieldes there be two wayes prepared, one faire, broad, pleaſant, careleſſe: the other foule, narrowe, tedious, hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and carefull. He that taketh his pleaſure on the waie, there is no reaſon he ſhould haue it at his iourneies ende. He that laboureth &amp; is in his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, will be merrie at night. This pleaſant way hath aſſayed many wiſe men, but allured none: For it aſſaulted <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> by incantation of <hi>Circe</hi> and <hi>Calypſo,</hi> by vocation of <hi>Syrens</hi> muſicke, by bitter ſweete delightes: ſuch as the voluptuous ladie preferred to our <hi>Hercules.</hi> If <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> had not diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed like a wiſe trauailer with <hi>Circe,</hi> and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the deepeſt propertie of an Oratour with <hi>Calypſo,</hi> and preuented in pollicie, by ſtopping his eares from the womaniſh harmonie of <hi>Syrens,</hi> in the one he had beene metamorphoſed with his whole Regiment into Bores and hogges and brute beaſtes (for ſuch are all men ſenſles in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes,) in the other he had beene tourned head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into the ſea for a pray to a ſight of hungrie fidlers, who neuer pyped better then when they lacked meat for their dinner. And then they plaied to picke ſuch noble mens purſes as <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> and bring their liues into a Sea of vtter deſtruction and want.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corydon,</hi> I deſire to know whie <hi>Tityrus</hi> being ſo faithful a friend vnto you, and ſo continually in your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie learneth not your vaine of ſpeaking,
<pb facs="tcp:8706:17"/> and ſpeaketh not more often.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tityrus</hi> my be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loued <hi>Tityrus,</hi> ſpeaketh ſeldome and therfore more wiſely. Herein I thanke you, that you reprehend my multiloqus and fribolus wordes: in deede hee that ſpeaketh much, offendeth much, and ſilence ſometimes is ſafe ſpeaking, for the tongue a little creature is too often a tall fellow of his handes, but the heart often maketh the heeles to bee nimble and the tongue ſpeakinge ſo much idlelie, leaueth nothing for the heart to ſaie or allowe: which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and turneth golden mines into leaden pigges, and often maketh a mountaine to bringe foorth a mouſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Am.</speaker>
               <p>Say no more of promiſes <hi>Corydon,</hi> for though you inſinuate thereby into the feeblenes of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens wittes, which are often drawne with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt delightes of mens ſubtiltie, and importunate flatterie to promiſe more then honeſtlie they may performe: Yet holding ſecond counſelles, with the friendes that belonge to their owne honour,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Cicero Philip. 12. poſteriores cogitationes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiores.</note> they anſwere you fooliſh ſwaines (who are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that euerie woman loues you that makes you beleeue ſo) howe that all promiſes are not to be kept. <hi>Nec omnia, nec nulla, nec non aliqua.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tityrus.</speaker>
               <p>Naie then <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> you diſparage the workes of fidelitie, which are inherent more in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous mindes, then in degenerous perſons: whoſe feare of ſome misfortune arguing their cowardize, doe not becauſe they dare not, performe all they promiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8706:17"/>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Naie doe not, becauſe they cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme anie ſuch haſtie promiſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tityrus.</speaker>
               <p>What call you promiſes in haſt that be not promiſes in waſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Promiſes in haſt are, when ſuters whoſe green attire profeſſe them to be Robin Hoods men: yet ſhoote in <hi>Cupids</hi> bowe at <hi>Dianas</hi> ſeruants. To them a tale of Robin Hood, and a promiſe ſent home, by Long the carrier belongeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>And when promiſe you in waſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>In waſt when the faith of promiſe oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the falſhood of men, makes them fullie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of loue at our handes, when they ſeeke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but luſte, and ſo beeing intangled with faire promiſes will thinke no more of foule actes. And ſo we induce them to waſt in fonde loue: becauſe they would induce vs to taſt of filthie luſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>For their vile regard of your honour, they haue a vile reward of your honeſtie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>Naie of our honeſtie, for they haue but ſmall honeſtie, that vſe men ſo diſhoneſtlie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Women are verie vngracious, becauſe men are verie vngratefull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>Men are verie vngratefull, becauſe women are verie vnfaithfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Women are verie politique, becauſe men are verie deceitfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>Men are verie deceitefull in deede, becauſe the women are verie beautifull indeede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Women are verie faire indeede, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:8706:18"/> men are verie falſe in worde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tityr.</speaker>
               <p>And women being verie faire in face, and not true in heart, are as their phyſiognomy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſageth of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amaryllis.</speaker>
               <p>Are you skilled in the phyſiognomie? as how I pray you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tityrus.</speaker>
               <p>If high in forehead, then women are high in minde, couragious like a Lyoneſſe, and verie liberall of one thing or other. And it importeth deſire of Empire and rule, and the gouernement to reſt in their feeble diſcretion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amaryllis.</speaker>
               <p>But how if they be contrarie, and in the forehead low?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tityrus.</speaker>
               <p>Then it ſignifieth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly lowe and baſe mindes, and ſorrowfull heartes, paſsionate and diſcontented, becauſe the blemiſh being in the faireſt place and moſt viſible cauſeth them to ſeek the darkeſt places, eſchewing companie to liue ſolitarie and inuiſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amaryllis.</speaker>
               <p>And what purporteth a frowning for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head with clowdie lookes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tityrus.</speaker>
               <p>It importeth boldneſſe, and in a woman foolehardines, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage Lyonlike (or if you will haue it) in deſire like a Bull, as in forehead like a Bull frowning: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo readie to wiſh her husband thoſe ornamentes which ſhould manifeſt to the worlde her ſecrete diſpoſition, not without ſome reaſon, for they are more fit for a man then for a woman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Well, paſſe on with your paſtoral diſcourſe &amp; skill to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of things beyond your Tarbox, and tell of the phyſiognomie of the eies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tityrus.</speaker>
               <p>Small Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits eies, ſhewe them to be toyiſh like Apes, as
<pb facs="tcp:8706:18"/> bigge ſetled, dull: vnſharp eies, ſhewe them to be ſluggiſh, vnwelding like a Cowe with a bonegrace on her head: hollowe eies, witchcraft full of ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and ſecret malice: great gogling eies, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes, for you know tis proper to an Aſſe. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a little hollowe, ſignifieth ſtout courage and magnanimitie like a Lyoneſſe. But if they be verie open and rowling, beware of impudencie: for it is one of the two viperous brood and daughters of my ladie Careleſſe, and Inſolencie is the other daughter: For as <hi>Tully</hi> hath, to neglect what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the world ſhall carrie about of you, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the propertie of an impudent creature, but of a diſſolute bodie. But to come to particulars, <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryllis,</hi> eies more fit for <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> deſcription are blacke, which ſignifieth no mutation but conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. In that they haue the litle Haſle circlet which doth inuiron and hedge in a golden fleece in the middeſt of your right eie, which ſhepherdes think to ſteale, if it ſpie them firſt, it depriueth them of all liuing ſence, leauing them onely vegetatiue ſence like vnto trees, becauſe of their preſumption, which are but markes to tell of the boldneſſe of them that went before, vnto them that ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe after. And in a worde, the whole phyſiog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie of the eies ſhall be in this ſentence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded: <hi>Quanto maior tanto minor malitia: ſed ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titia maior.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amaryllis.</speaker>
               <p>I like your Roſemarie you giue mee <hi>Tityrus,</hi> but not your Fenell. Let vs heare
<pb facs="tcp:8706:19"/> of the lippes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>They cannot be deuided except they were firſt cloſed; nor can not be deſcribed, except they be diſcloſed: and cannot be diſcloſed openlie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they be touched ſecretlie. Therefore faire <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maryllis,</hi> ſith euer you haue repelled mee from the one, blame me not though I faile in the other, for honour me firſt in this, and honour wil nouriſhe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes. <hi>Tantalus</hi> hath not anie nice taſte, if he haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at all: nor <hi>Siſiphus</hi> any knowledge of the Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas holidaies, if he knowe of anie: nor anie ende of his labour, if he haue anie ende of his water and worke. Wherefore that I maie report of Paradiſe, let me taſt of <hi>Euphrates:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. In vanis oſculis ſuauis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, Theocritus.</note> for there is in one of the ſenſes of taſting, all the liberall ſciences of learning. And in vaine kiſſing true pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>You are beſides your manners, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I maruell not to ſee you beſides your matters. But in conceite vſe your pleaſure, ſo you maie by imputation be admitted to be bleſſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall thereby be as happie as the Hacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie man is, who often is as poore as <hi>Irus,</hi> becauſe often his Horſes are of the colour of <hi>Iris,</hi> which in deede is no colour, as they are often to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not with him. As to mee you vſe the worde conceite, ſo to him they vſe the deede de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite. And they ſaie to him as you ſaie to me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue well and haue well. <hi>Sic ego reſcribo de tuo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frido, crede quod habes &amp; habes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Well nowe you maie returne from your
<pb facs="tcp:8706:19"/> pleaſure, and deſcribe the want of your pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tityrus.</speaker>
               <p>In a worde, the lippes are praiſed as pleaſe euery man to like of them. And there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heed to be taken, then that they open not their wardes for feare leſt they let out many out of their dungeon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Many what?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>Many charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able priſoners, which will cauſe a heauie action to lie againſt the perſon, I meane corrupt words, for which all men may condemne one, or corrupt breath, from which all men will commend one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>You are diſpoſed to enioyne my abſence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>No, <hi>Amaryllis</hi> rather to enioy your preſence. I will proceede if <hi>Tityrus</hi> will not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>do ſo, &amp; I will clime with admiration vp into the faire bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this tall <hi>Caſtanea</hi> tree, from which by that time <hi>Corydon</hi> hath told my tale by <hi>Arithmetike,</hi> I can deduct three little ſprigs, and then <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> &amp; this goodly tree wilbe of one name and nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Lips which be ſoft and ſmooth and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourlike kiſſe eche other, ſignifie vnitie and redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to wage battell againſt the rauening Lyons that would rudely pray vpon their cheries. Such are yours <hi>Amaryllis.</hi> Thoſe that are verie hard and rugged and blewe like a Saphire, declare that ſwine liue vpon the Acornes which they find vnder eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tree, where for a meſſe of commons in <hi>Epicurus</hi> kitchin, they open their quiuer to euerie mans ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe. A verie thick vpper lippe hanging ouer too much, is neuer troubled with too much wit. And a thicke vpper lip turning vpward that the gumme
<pb facs="tcp:8706:20"/> may be perceiued, is conſtrued by the ſimilitude of ſnarling to be a dogg, at leaſt a reprochefull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>And what of the noſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>The tippe of the noſe being fleſhie, ſignifieth no worſe matter then fleſhly luſt: But turning vp withall, ſignifieth by compariſon a Swyne, &amp; in veritie it noteth ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhnes. The tippe being ſharp foreſheweth, as the prouerbe of (Mucteriſme) <hi>Naſuti homines</hi> telleth, an angrie Scoffer:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to be a ſecrete ſcoffer. Of that kinde of noſe, read Plinie. li. 11. cap 32.</note> And as the noſe of a Woolfe, it ſheweth ſecret crueltie. For the noſtrels if they are wide, they ſignifie Lyonlike &amp; full of force. Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row noſtrels are full of motions as children, and by compariſon of birdes apt to ſing ſweetely, becauſe vnapter to let the ſound through the noſe. A noſe flat to the face, &amp; crooked importeth often a croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked bodie, &amp; by the compariſon of a carren Crow ſhameleſſe, and a light huſwife. But in this deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a flat noſe, a certaine writer hath many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ſtill Nurture amendeth Nature. On the contrarie, if crooked Eglelike, then high minded but lowe couraged. <hi>Simonaſed</hi> is libidinous. Alſo broad noſed, is furious. But louelie long noſed rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching downward toward the mouth, preſageth all the vertues in <hi>Tullies Offices,</hi> &amp; eſpecially fortitude.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quàm ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis turpiſſima beltia nobis.</note>And what of the eares.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>litle, like an Ape. Great, like an Aſſe. Flapping, like a foole. But mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate eares are naturall to all people, and ſhewe ſome moderation in the reſt of the ſenſes, if the ſences be framed accordingly. Verie round eares are verie vnfit to learne. And verie long eares, are
<pb facs="tcp:8706:20"/> verie enuious. And verie much cleauing to ones head, are of ſome vnknowen ill diſpoſition. If heares be in the eares, then apter to heare quickly: From whence our terme hearing may be taken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amaryllis.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe tell mee in generall, what ſhape of the face and countenance is beſt deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate by dame Nature vnto women.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Corydon.</speaker>
               <p>If fleſhie, then ſomewhat ſluggiſh: If leane, then cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, If bigg and foggie, fearefull like an Aſſe, or as the Hart is. If round and ſomewhat fat with a little blacke ſpot or two on it, then faire <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> The roundnes ſheweth aptnes of proportion, as a temple of better giftes which are within. And the reaſon why the ſpottes are, is that a little contrarie oppoſed to a marueilous ſingularitie, doth make that which is verie excellent to be better: becauſe the imperfection ſtanding neere beauties grace is made a leſſe imperfection, and beautie a more beautie. As blacke annexed to white, maketh white more white, and blacke more perfecte blacke.</p>
               <p>Now for the countenance, if it looke downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; groueling, tis a ſigne of an Hypocrit, &amp; of diſcontented wickednes. And a drunken counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, a drunkard: an angrie countenance, a bed-lame: and on the contrarie, a ſhamefaſt counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, a gracious woman. Any one that is defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med is ill manerd likely, if Nurture be not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant ouer Nature: as <hi>Therſytes</hi> of whom the Poets ſay <hi>venerat ad Troiam quo non deformior alter.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8706:21"/> And of all that be correſpondent in manners, in a prouerbe they call it <hi>Therſitica facies:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Therſites was caled <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> one that defo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med his face with haſtie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ring like a Rauen as the worde doth ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie in Ariſt. lib 9. Anim. ca. 24.</note> A verie large viſage is vnſhamefaſt. Thoſe that ſweat in the face with ſmall motions, may haue ſmall honeſtie. But often times they are craftie, and ſtill they are great eaters. Verie little round faces ſignifie ſimplicitie. Verie crooked long leane faces are malicious, but onely for profits ſake. And <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> you haue hereby a glaſſe to decerne your choice, but not ſo ſure as a touchſtone to trie gold by. For neither is all gold that gliſtereth, nor all that aſhes that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth:<note place="margin">Saepe ſub. cinere doloſo latet ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. Horat. ergo caue. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Lucret ex The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophraſto.</note> but often gold is hid in earth: and often vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der deceitpfull aſhes lie coles of fire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Why then I perceiue no aſſurance of iudgement but vncerteine geſſe to be in the phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognomie of women, and all your proofes to be like the Phyſitions iudgement of a womans inferiour partes by her water. It is not of the neceſſitie of his ſcience to knowe more by the water then is done aboue the gyrdleſteede, nor of your Arte to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne more then you ſee apparant in the face. And that you deſcribe out of your ſhepherdes Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Whereby you can tell, if you ſee a cloud, that it is a ſigne of a ſhowre, and many ſtarres bring a froſt: and the euening red, a faire morning: and the morning gray, a faire euening. And by the backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone of a Woodcocke, you can tell aſwell as the Woodcockes ſelfe, what weather ſhall inſue: But by looking in ones face, you cannot tell what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſhee hath in her purſe. Your ſcience makes
<pb facs="tcp:8706:21"/> you often in hope of a faire weather to clime the mountaines where the Muſes ſtand with goads in their handes to repel you ſwaines, and you forſake the baſe and humble valleis which are more fit for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Corydon.</speaker>
               <p>This and more of <hi>Amaryllis</hi> will her true hearted ſwaine indure, onely impatient of this, that I ſhould haue <hi>Tityrus</hi> my Riuall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>Onely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of this, that I ſhould haue <hi>Corydon</hi> my Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Wherefore I pray you: <hi>Dicite Riualem vix ego ferre Iouem. Amaryllis.</hi> No, I am onely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacient in this, that you ſhould ſtriue about no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Are you nothing <hi>Amaryllis?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I am no ſuch thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Why not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I am not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That is a womans ſimple reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>It is a good and ſubtill reaſon. For in all things that are ſo, your ſenſes ought to take notice that they are ſo, and not to call in queſtion why they are ſo:<note place="margin">Libro <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ariſto. lib. 1. Analyt.</note> For your <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath it in his wiſedome, that <hi>Senſus nulla de re cur ita ſit indicat.</hi> As if it be fire, no reaſon to aske why it is hoat: but onely to haue relation to the effect of the thing. As if it be fire, to know that it is hoat: if water, to knowe that it is colde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>And if a woman, to knowe that ſhee is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>And if faire, to knowe, that ſhee may be falſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>And if a man, to know that he knowes manie more then women, and therefore he that is euery where, they ſay he is worthy to be no where.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tity.</speaker>
               <p>How know you that men know many things?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe many things are knowen of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8706:22"/>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Why, that is the ſame by the ſame, which is no good reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>So is their knowledge the ſame by the ſame, which is no good order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>How?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>As to know the yonger by the elder.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Blame not men therein <hi>Amaryllis.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Why by what rule <hi>Corydon?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe newe wine hath often an olde garland.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>I but good wine neede no garlande, nor good women any ſuch cuſtomers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well, for they are knowen as well without a Poeſie in their breſtes, as if they had it written within their Rings: <hi>Vireſco ſemper vulnere.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>But tel me <hi>Corydon,</hi> by what priuie marke of countenance I may know the complexion and diſpoſition of ſuch creatures?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>In the male, note a bonnye-face leane, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a dailaborer, &amp; a man of a cold nature by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of manie loſſes at ſea.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>How at ſea?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What Sea you will, either the Sea where Flemiſh hoyes beare Engliſh burthens: or Engliſh hoyes beare the French loading, whether you will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Am.</speaker>
               <p>And how in a woman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In a woman, if ſhee be ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, who of nature ſhould be ſhamefaſte. And though in a man, the face is almoſt immutable: yet in ſuch a woman verie ſoone <hi>Vultus mutatur, na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lando dicitur.</hi> Their countenance is comming and going: for it is deriued of a fugitiue word, by reaſon that euery Arte hath ſpeciall termes to expreſſe it. If ſhee looke yll, you may ſoone perceiue it: for the countenance is a certeine ſylent ſpeech and dombe ſhewe to declare what the minde and the bodie are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8706:22"/>
               <speaker>Amaryllis.</speaker>
               <p>I but is all this any thing certeine that you haue tolde mee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo ſure as neuer otherwiſe. But this knowe <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> that theſe thinges are moſt apparant in men &amp; women, ſuch as are not regenerate and waſhed from the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Nature: As in the <hi>Adamites,</hi> whoſe hard heartes want mortifying of gouernement: <hi>Naturae ſequitur ſemina quiſque ſuae.</hi> Euerie man followeth his inſtillation of Nature. The vſe of Phyſiogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie is verie auncient: For <hi>Iacob</hi> the father of all ſhepherdes tolde by <hi>Labans</hi> phyſiognomie vnto his wiues, what minde <hi>Laban</hi> bare towardes him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amaryllis.</speaker>
               <p>Then I ſee ſome certeintie to be in the ſcience. But in a worde, giue me the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a comely perſon, and of a deformed crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, what they are noted throughout all partes to be in both ſex.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Corydon.</speaker>
               <p>In a worde, a woman faire in all partes without ſome ſecrete or hidden blemiſh, cannot be without faire conditions and honeſt: for ſhee is called of the Primotor of all things <hi>Man hu:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reſpond. Danum Dei.</note> as one deformed in the leaſt ſort, is not without ſome fault notorious: So is it of all people an old ſaide ſawe, and prouerbially true: <hi>Diſtortum vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſequitur distantia morum.</hi> Of them beware, whome God hath any waie noted in the face or elſe where. They that are not deformed, are more like their Creator, whoſe perfection in his creatures ſhewes him to be without blemiſh or deformitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8706:23"/>
               <p>By this you haue a faire caueat to beware the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection in ſhape of <hi>Tityrus</hi> my fellowe ſwayne, whom you haue often noted for his ſauage lookes, and loue you the ſimplicitie of <hi>Corydon</hi> whom you haue found, though ſomewhat mutable, yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies honeſt in indeuour to perfourme his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though in deede, too ſhort of his dutie. And if time ſhall heale greifes by killing of care, then <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> my herdes of Deere, and flockes of ſheep mounted vpon mine owne hils, where my little manſion is, euen Tame like ſheepe intangled as are their leaders thoughtes, ſhall waite vpon you to paie their owne ranſome with their deareſt bloud.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I but <hi>Corydon,</hi> ſhall not I waite too long vpon them firſt? Care is yet but yong, and therefore ſtrong ynough to fight with Time, and Time is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a deuourer of mens expectations, then a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of their griefes: for to gape for dead mens ſhooes is often to goe barefoot. And whiles your parkes may be cloathed with <hi>Flora,</hi> &amp; your woods armed with ſtrength: and your Swannes that in <hi>Leander</hi> at the bottom of your mount do ſurmount in number, we may be laughed at by your pleaſant fieldes that ſhall be for our preſent follie that is, &amp; may be blowed coldly vpon by your boyſterous Okes, yet haue we no aucthoritie to control them with the Axe. And your louely Swannes muing themſelues vnder your chamber windowe, may make vs wiſh our enuious eyes were out, rather then to be hold ſo much future pleaſure, &amp; ſo little
<pb facs="tcp:8706:23"/> preſent ioy. And what were this for vs to be in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of elder Care as his children continually? You be gotten as it were of his owne marrowe, I adopted to be the daughter of Care for loue of you. You in want of maintenance to liue a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds life: I in want of ſuſtenance to die a lingring death: or if lingring in ſubiection cannot happilie die, but muſt in viewing about your bitter ſweete delights, behold any of mine owne conſort, as the Nightingale which now in my virginitie carrieth no fether to her neſt, but asketh leaue firſt of me, to accompanie her with the noates of my ſimple voice, that thereby the labour may ſeeme more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, yet then I ſhall ſee them carrie apace, but muſt needs thinke as they poore they do: That not for me, but for others this neſt is built: for the profites are ſtill our elder Cares. We ſhould ſee the Bees haue their working thoughts &amp; their thighes loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Treaſure to our fightes: and as they ſaye, we muſt ſay: not for our ſelues but for others. See the wanton Fawnes skipping to fat themſelues with ſpeed, and as they ſay we ſay: not for vs but for others. See the plentifull &amp; gratefull ſheepe for their bare ſuſtenance render this maintenance: vd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſtrowting with milke including farther profit, moſt fit nouriſhment for our infants: fleeces on their backes, whereof the fineſt cloth is made: ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der carcaſes, wheron the fineſt people feed: marks on their foreheads, which meane not for our gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſhepherds, but for our cruell maſters the elder
<pb facs="tcp:8706:24"/> Care. Wee may ſee the trauailing Oxe worke out with feare and trembling his own deſtruction. And ſo all things wee may ſee but nothing we muſt haue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>O but <hi>Amaryllis!</hi> tis ſomewhat to go halting by Nature, better then not to go at all. And better haue half a loafe then no bread. And that ſo wee enioy loue for euer: Let vs indure pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience for a while. Our pleaſures wil be more then common perſons are. I am noblie deſcended though ſauagely I liue. All mine is all yours which to enumerate wil be comfort, though yet not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie. Faire houſes without large rents: great parks without trouble of tillage, both ſeated ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in a rich prouince: which euer as now they are, ſo were they the <hi>Granare</hi> &amp; ſtorehouſe of prouiſion and victuals to all our Ilande: From whence the whole people of <hi>Crotona</hi> haue tranſported vſually to comfort the borderers in annual reliefe, an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſaile of boates and lighters loaden with grain. But leſt the praiſe of mine owne countrey ſeduce my penne to lauiſh, and leſt I ſhould be carped at to write our incredible perfection by reaſon of my vnſpeakable affection: I intreat your ſweete con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration to accept in good parte the confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our bleſſedneſſe by mine owne relation. For natiue ſoyle carries away euerie ſence with deſire of delight to praiſe it and pray for it.</p>
               <p>O moſt happie dominion, whoſe hap it was to be more bleſſed then any other parte of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent. Thou art the prime &amp; the chiefeſt that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held
<pb facs="tcp:8706:24"/> the renowmed <hi>Constantinus Caeſar.</hi> In thee he left his Hart for liking, and his Hind for feeding. On the one thy name was written for remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: on the necke of the other, his name was written for aſſurance. Nature hath repaide thee thy deſert beyond thy deſire, thou art indued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the fruites of the earth, and all the fauour of the ayre, in thee the rewardes of ſeede are ſo plentiful, that <hi>Ceres</hi> hath her barnes indued with graine, and <hi>Bacchus</hi> his preſſe fulfilled with grape, in whome are huge woodes to couer, without hydeous beaſtes to deuour: in whome are fertile groundes to manure for foode, without feareful ſerpentes to procure death. Againe, of ſillie &amp; gentle &amp; profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſheepe, ſo great is the multitude, that for their bare food, as hating ingratitude, they yeeld fleeces fit for <hi>Iaſons</hi> labour, or from their backs for <hi>Corydons</hi> hyre, vdders for <hi>Corydon</hi> and <hi>Amaryllis</hi> children, which only they hold vp, till that day with groning to haue none but <hi>Amaryllis</hi> infants play with their yong ones: And none but <hi>Amaryllis</hi> ſeruaunts to bring down their pride &amp; ſwelling teates: To make cruds &amp; cum-butter &amp; walwhay only for <hi>Amaryllis</hi> dairie. Saue that they rather chooſe to loſe their wool on bryers for charities ſake to the poore, then that their maſters elder Care ſhould ſheare them too too neare for couetouſnes. And they wil often counterfait ſickenes before their time, to be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the releefe of the poore, rather then their maiſters elder Care ſhould take them home to infect their
<pb facs="tcp:8706:25"/> ſhepherds with the rott of Mutton: for old Care is euer more couetous then yong Careleſſe is prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall. Touching that which all men hate the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe our Climate is daily preuented with that which al men loue the lightnes, for we haue none but humble valleis vnto our champion, &amp; no fence for which the daytide being of great length, the night is neuer without ſome lightnes: Except at ſuch time of the night as the vttermoſt plaines of the earth, receiue no light, then when as the goall of night and of the heauens is ouercome, and that the ſtarlight departeth euen in the interceſſion of the newe day. In ſo much as the Sunne which to all other people ſeemeth to go downe and fall, to vs appeareth but ſtill to paſſe away. Sith then <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryllis,</hi> this is creat onely to beare flowers for my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land which I meane to beſtowe yerely vpon you, as a Coronet for your patience, till I can indow you with the whole, I requeſt you, accept my abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie as a poſſibilitie, though not a poſſeſsion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich you withall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
               <p>Yes <hi>Corydon,</hi> I take well in worth your ſingular curteſies, but may not breake <hi>Veſta</hi> her lawes for loue of <hi>Ceres,</hi> nor leaue <hi>Diana</hi> her grace to ſeeke <hi>Lucinas</hi> helpe, nor leaue foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of <hi>Nectar</hi> to taſt riuers of water, nor leaue <hi>Manna</hi> to taſt of <hi>Ambroſia.</hi> But as I haue put on the ſtoale &amp; Robe of dignitie, ſo muſt I learn to ſhunne indignitie, for I haue many eies obiect vpon mee: eies ſuch as the Pecocke doeth ſpread to enuie faire weather &amp; proſperitie: eies ſuch as can faſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb facs="tcp:8706:25"/> the tender lambes of <hi>Diana,</hi> and for their pleaſure haue induced them to aduerſitie eies that are poreblinde, and therefore looke nigh vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Eies that are bleared and ſo cannot ſee into themſelues. Eies like the Owle to ſee what is done in the night. Eies like the Stare to watch for the daie. Eies like the Hawke, to watch aloft for a fowle. Eies like a Buzard, at hand to ſeaſe vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing. Eies of a Doue, but eares withall. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of little Pytchardes, they haue great eares. And therefore it behooueth me to borrowe of the Eagle her eies, that I may behold the Sunne &amp; not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded of the glorie. And becauſe it is a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome among <hi>Dianas</hi> ſeruants to banquet much in honour of our miſtris, I do vſe to repreſſe that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious god with a more ſober:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and mingle water with my wine, which in taking away that which is hurtfull, doth leaue onely that which is healthfull. And becauſe there hath bin the <hi>Mandrage</hi> a ſtarke poyſon growing neare vnto Vines in many coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, I vſe to giue euery one leaue to drinke thriſe for my once. I haue read in a writer of a certaine Pearle, which I meane to ſend for ſhortly,<note place="margin">Plinius lib. 25. cap. 9. li 14. c. 2. Plutarch lib. de Audi. poetis. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> called <hi>Amethuſton,</hi> to hang at mine eare: they ſay it doth vſe to repell deſires. Some were vſed to receiue into their bodies <hi>Amuletos</hi> before ſuch times as they went to banket, and ſome to carrie it about them, it will ſurely repell ouerſight in drinking, or ouerdelight in eating. Theſe experiences ſith I haue learned firſt of you <hi>Corydon,</hi> I will reſt your
<pb facs="tcp:8706:26"/> ſcholler ſtill for your vertues, but no louer of anie ones perſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Why then my ſong ſhall be of patience perforce, and I will ſtill be attendant vpon your preferment, though I meane to goe hide my ſhame in my fathers woods, that once might not haue repented mee too late, but haue releeued my true loue in time, euen with the enioying of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryllis,</hi> whoſe ioyes nowe increaſed ſhall increaſe my bad Muſe to intreate of them day and night. And nowe both you fountaines &amp; drierie woods, lende of the infinite ſoundes and innumerable buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes in you, a verſe for euerie budde, and a line for euerie leafe. And you immeaſurable mountaines in heighth expreſsing my high deſire in euer-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing greenes, manifeſting my eternall good will, in hugenes remembring her impoſsiblenes of me nowe to be embraced: in hauing but one waye to go vp, and that verie narrowe, it foreſheweth that onely vertue muſt be the path that leadeth vnto her: In being ſtored with Cedar trees, foretelleth mee, that ſhee inclyneth to high honours: In be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtored with ſheepe, ſayeth ſhee ſhall be riche: In hauing a fountaine, ſheweth ſhee hath wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: In hauing humble and lowe vallies, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that ſhee hath true humilitie: In bearing the name of <hi>Pimplea,</hi> aſſureth the beholders, that none muſt preſume before they be called, leſt they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by her ſwaines with their hookes, and by her maynie with their whips. You ſenceles creatures receiue mee into your herd for as mute a creature,
<pb facs="tcp:8706:26"/> though not ſo brute a ſubſtance as you, till I being well acquainted with your kinde, yeeld glorie to my miſtreſſe for making mee ſilent, as you do to your creator for making you a ſubiect. Yet not ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Corydon</hi> til I haue ſaid my mind, once more to moue her ſpirites to ſing vnto my Roundilay her mornings tune, which putting vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with her gown all grauitie, ſhee may vſe to modulat to this dittie.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                  <body>
                     <head>Corydons Hymne to the praiſe of <hi>Amaryllis.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Would mine eies were criſtall fountaines</l>
                     <l>Where you might the ſhadow view:</l>
                     <l>Of my griefes like to theſe mountaines</l>
                     <l>Swelling for the loſſe of you.</l>
                     <l>Cares which cureleſſe are alas,</l>
                     <l>Helpleſſe, hapleſſe for they grow,</l>
                     <l>Cares like tares the number paſſe,</l>
                     <l>All the ſeede that loue doth ſowe.</l>
                     <l>Who but could remember all,</l>
                     <l>Twinkling eies ſtill repreſenting</l>
                     <l>Starres, which pearce mee to the gall,</l>
                     <l>Cauſe they lend no lenger lighting,</l>
                     <l>And your <hi>Nectar</hi> lips alluring,</l>
                     <l>Humane ſence to tast of heauen.</l>
                     <l>For no art of mans manuring,</l>
                     <l>Finer ſilke hath euer weauen,</l>
                     <l>Who but could remember this,</l>
                     <l>The ſweet odors of your fauour:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8706:27"/>
                     <l>When I ſmeld I was in bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>Neuer felt I ſweeter ſauour.</l>
                     <l>And your harmles hart annointed,</l>
                     <l>As the custome was of Kings:</l>
                     <l>Showes your ſacred ſoule appointed,</l>
                     <l>To be prime of earthly things.</l>
                     <l>Ending thus remember all,</l>
                     <l>Clothed in a mantle greene,</l>
                     <l>Tis ynough I am your thrall,</l>
                     <l>Leaue to thinke what eye hath ſeene.</l>
                     <l>Yet the eie may not ſo leaue,</l>
                     <l>Though the thought do ſtill repine:</l>
                     <l>but muſt gaſe till death bequeath,</l>
                     <l>Eies &amp; thoughtes vnto their ſhryne.</l>
                     <l>Which if <hi>Amaryllis</hi> chaunce</l>
                     <l>Hearing to make haſte to ſee,</l>
                     <l>To life death ſhee may aduaunce,</l>
                     <l>Therefore eies &amp; thoughts go free.</l>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Now <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> ending my mirth, beginnes my moane. Now departing from your ſight, I ſhall be blinde, and from your preſence I ſhall periſh. Yet vouchſafe beauties wanton darling, ſo called for that you haue beene pleaſant with my Kiddes, and learned to ſmile quickly of dame <hi>Flora</hi> your grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, ſuffer my thoughtes to be ſent as ſuters to your honour to protect their baſenes, though my bodie be abſent from your ſight, by reaſon of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines. Nowe I haue fed a wanton eie, I will go feede my ſtarued flocke: and ſith greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie
<pb facs="tcp:8706:27"/> is befallen <hi>Amaryllis</hi> then my infirmitie muſt thinke, of my accuſtomed boldnes ſhall not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch your preſence without ſome preſent, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to gratifie ſo high degree. All this while <hi>Tity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> gathers my ſtraying flockes to his ſtraying thoughtes, &amp; keepes my Kiddes from pride which would inſult, ſith they haue notice of <hi>Amaryllis</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. But let <hi>Tityrus</hi> my beloued Riuall, beware leſt that <hi>Libyan</hi> white one, which wanting a play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow, and going to <hi>Amaryllis</hi> fountaine to ſeeke her, do not fall into a phrenſie for abſence of his foſter mother, and ſo ſtrike him ſodaynly with her horne. O gracious <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> why do you recall me your <hi>quondam</hi> louer, roming like the Woodoſes in theſe groues, to view that you muſt flie them, and go to <hi>Dianas</hi> courtes? Do you hate me? No. Then you muſt loue mee. True. For in <hi>Dianas</hi> nymphes there is but two diſpoſitions, and in a woman ther is no third thing: <hi>Mulier aut amat, aut odit, nihil eſt tertium.</hi> Then do ſo ſtill. Shall I be the ſame in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour when I come to mans ſtate, as now being a beardleſſe youth? Then deſtroy me preſently that I may die before the cogitations of departure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue me of my ioyfull bliſſe. Behold, I caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee twelue Queenapples, though the Gods ſent down but one, all pourporting this poeſie: To the faireſt of twelue. I gathered them from a tree planted with thine owne hand, which makes them looke ſo like heauenly foode. Beholde my bitter griefe. Why hide you your face <hi>Amaryllis?</hi> Would
<pb facs="tcp:8706:28"/> I were made a humming Bee to ſerue <hi>Dianas</hi> hyues, that ſo in her mount garden I might ſee my <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryllis</hi> mounted, wearing her daily garland, knotted with her owne haire, to ſhewe how ſhee hates to weare anie other bodies <hi>Thyrſus.</hi> Nowe do I know O loue, that thou art a plagie god. Certes, ſome Lyoneſſe was thy foſter mother (or elſe the Poets faine) when <hi>Iaculus</hi> &amp; you ranne away from your own mother. Or elſe you were <hi>Aſtyages</hi> ſonne, one of the firſt Monarchie that was, whom when your mother was with childe of you, your father dreamed that ſhee bare a Vinebranch in her womb that would ouerſhadowe all <hi>Aſia:</hi> Asking coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Soothſayers what brood ſhee ſhoulde breed: they tolde true, ſuch an one as would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe all Nations, and depoſede your own father from rule of himſelfe. Then he gaue thee, O <hi>Cupid</hi> to <hi>Harpagus</hi> to be ouerwhelmed with the obliuious waues of the Sea. But he vnhappie engine of all mens woe, returning into a wood in vnlucky <hi>Perſia,</hi> there left thee at randome, to the wide worlde. Then <hi>Spacon,</hi> which in the <hi>Perſian</hi> language is a dogge, was thy Nurſe, and ſo art thou cruell by his education.</p>
               <p>Such an one is Loue, that whom a mad dogge byteth, he is madde preſently vppon it. I burning with inwarde fire, ſeeking with outward teares to quench the outward apparant flame of loue, my teares ſerue to ſmother my heat, the ſmoke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is the ſooner ſeene. So outwarde medicines
<pb facs="tcp:8706:28"/> ſhewe there to be inwarde griefes. Faire loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king like the glorious Diamond, in worth the moſt precious Pearle, Nymphe embrace a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde with your lookes, then they may kiſſe mee, though I not them, with the lippes of admiration. In faire lookes, are vayled with modeſtie ſweete kiſſes.</p>
               <p>I will go gather a Coronet, and will weaue &amp; infolde it with the knottes of trueſt loue, with greene lawrell <hi>Apollos</hi> ſcepter, which ſhall beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her wiſedome, and with the Myrtle faire <hi>Venus</hi> Poeſie, which ſhall ſhewe her beautie. And with <hi>Amaranthus Dianas</hi> herbe, whereby bloud is ſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, ſo may ſhee imitate the herbe, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce. Wo is mee, what <hi>Aetna</hi> ſhall I poſſeſſe. Will not <hi>Amaryllis</hi> heare? Then off goes my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral robes made of my deareſt Goates cloathing, and into this <hi>Lethe</hi> I runne, where if I be not drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yet eternall forgetfulneſſe ſhall make mee happie. Yet there the fiſher <hi>Olpis</hi> ſtill watching, may take mee to be the great fiſhe <hi>Thynnus,</hi> and ſo ſaue my life, and bring mee to ſhame againe. But I will do it, for then ſure I am, that ſome pleaſure in hope that I am dead will poſſeſſe <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryllis:</hi> ſo ſhee retourning with ioy to ſee, I maye take her in her good mood. All is in vaine, <hi>Diana</hi> calleth, and honour allureth. Lately, I asked counſell of <hi>Agraeo</hi> a Propheteſſe, howe to knowe whether <hi>Amaryllis</hi> ſhoulde euer loue mee, ſhee taught mee to take <hi>Telephilon</hi> a kinde of leafe that
<pb facs="tcp:8706:29"/> Pepper beareth ſo called of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe it fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheweth loue, and to clap the leaues in the palme of my hand. If they yeelded a great ſound, then ſurely ſhee ſhould loue me greatly: if a little ſound, then little loue. But either I was deafe being ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les through loue: or elſe no ſound at all was heard, and ſo <hi>Agraeo</hi> the diuinatrix tolde me a true rule. Nowe I preferre my garlande made in ſorrowfull haſt, of which the flowers, ſome ſignifying death, &amp; ſom mourning, but none belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to marriage, do manifeſt, that <hi>Amaryllis</hi> hath no reſpect of meane men. Come gentle <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> I wil go fetch that milkewhite Goat, which hath nowe a twinne which you haue euer liked, &amp; ſacrifice her to your liking. Will you not? Then <hi>Erithacis</hi> rich though not ſo faire, who is an earneſt ſuter to me ſhal haue them, becauſe ſhee is delighted with my preſence. But my right eie watreth, tis a ſigne of ſomewhat, do I ſee her yet. O faire <hi>Amaryllis,</hi> be not angrie, though I talke idlely, and ſpeake like one diſtract. At the foote of this Pine tree, I will ende my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, where perhaps ſhee may looke backe and ſee mee; for ſhee is no Adamant. I would I could preuent her ſwift pace as <hi>Hippomanes</hi> did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Atalanta,</hi> with golden Apples which <hi>Venus</hi> hath ſent mee to caſt before her, that ſhee ſtooping to golde, might be ouertaken. But gold cannot tempt Chaſtitie. I would with <hi>Bias</hi> make ſhift to obtaine faire <hi>Perones,</hi> though the Oracles ſaid I ſhould die for it, if I take the labour in taske. But ſhee ſeeketh
<pb facs="tcp:8706:29"/> not the death of a louer. I would with <hi>Adonis</hi> one of mine owne facultie, for loue of <hi>Venus</hi> watch ſo long in the woods, that the wilde bore ſhould ſlay mee for my duetie. But ſhee hating to be called <hi>Venus,</hi> wil rather let me continue dead then reuiue mee for loues ſake, as <hi>Venus</hi> did her <hi>Adonis.</hi> I would be like <hi>Endymion</hi> if I could, who for that he eſchu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all loue, and followed <hi>Dianas</hi> life, he fell in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light with perpetuall hunting in the woods. But <hi>Amaryllis</hi> will not be <hi>Luna</hi> to induce me into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſleepe, to the intent to imbrace mee: but will be <hi>Luna</hi> to the intent to flie from mee. I would be <hi>Iaſon</hi> if ſhee would be <hi>Ceres,</hi> and vouchſafe to ſleepe with mee,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> quaſi <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> then might ſhee be <hi>Ceres</hi> in deede <hi>quaſi Geres:</hi> but that were admirable, that by one bare ſleepe ſhould happen, yet might ſhee be <hi>Ceres</hi> for ſhee beareth glad tydings vnto him that ſhall haue her. Thus I fainting, and ſhee not caring, muſt thinke that what is hapleſſe ſhould be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, but that will not be. Then heere will I lye and let my flocke ſtarue, that when the Wolfe hath ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them, he may be ſo good vnto mee. This ſhal pleaſe <hi>Amaryllis</hi> rather then continuall importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet departing; honie of the Combe ſhal be my food: yet will I eate nothing but ſweete thoughts: and the ioyce of Pieres ſhalbe my drinke, yet will I drinke nothing but the ſpring water that ſhee laſt waſhed in. Where by the puritie, I ſhal thinke of her ſinceritie, and ſee my ſorrowes written in the ſandes. Here will I waite &amp; haunt theſe plaines &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:8706:30"/> woods, looking for no companion, but the louing birde which delighteth to behold the face of a man, of him I will loue to behold the face of a goddeſſe. Heere ſhal I finde none to tune vnto mee but that ladies birde that counterfaiteth to chatter with a ſmall ſhrill voyce as they do, &amp; faines the voice of a Ladie, to whom I will vſe to ſaie: O the voice of a goddeſſe! And whiles <hi>Tityrus</hi> is with our flock in <hi>Crotona,</hi> I will ſit heere till I ſee <hi>Diana</hi> come bie, &amp; will bethinke mee vpon a number of <hi>Hieroglyphiks,</hi> which I will compoſe in ſome order ſhortly, and preferre them to <hi>Amaryllis.</hi> In the meane while, let this my Roundilay end my follie.</p>
            </sp>
            <lg>
               <l>Sith the Nimphs are thought to be happie creatures,</l>
               <l>For that at faier <hi>Helicon</hi> a Fountaine,</l>
               <l>Where all vſe like white Ritch Iuorie foreheads</l>
               <l>Daily to ſprinckle,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sith the quire of Muſes atend <hi>Diana,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Euer vſe to bathe heauie thoughts refyning,</l>
               <l>With the Siluer skinne, Ciuet &amp; Mir vſing,</l>
               <l>For their adornment,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sith my ſacred Nymphs priuiledge abateth,</l>
               <l>Cauſe <hi>Dianas</hi> grace did elect the <hi>Myrtle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To be pride of euery branch in order</l>
               <l>laſt of her handmaides:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Should then I thus liue to behold euerted,</l>
               <l>Skies with impure eyes in a fountaine harbourd,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Titans</hi> honor ſeated is as vnder</l>
               <l>All the beholders?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:8706:30"/>
               <l>Helpe wofull <hi>Ecco,</hi> reabound relenting,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Dianas</hi> grace on her helpe recalling,</l>
               <l>May well heare thy voice to bewaile, reanſwere</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Amaryllis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fairer in deede then <hi>Galataea,</hi> faireſt</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Dianas</hi> troope to bewitch the wiſeſt,</l>
               <l>With amaſing eye to abandon humors</l>
               <l>of any Gallants.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee <hi>Thetis</hi> faier, <hi>Galataea</hi> modeſt,<note place="margin">Poſſis ſimul Thetide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lataeam amar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſet. voluptatem &amp; gloriam, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Prouerbium.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Albeit ſome ſaye in a Chryſtall often,</l>
               <l>Tis a rule, there lurketh a deadly poyſon,</l>
               <l>Tis but a falſe rule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For what Yſe is hid in a Diamond Ring,</l>
               <l>Where the wiſe beholder hath eyes refuſing,</l>
               <l>Allabaſters vaines to no workeman hidden,</l>
               <l>Gold to no Touchſtone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There bedeckes faireſt <hi>Roſamond</hi> the fountaine,</l>
               <l>Where reſorts thoſe greene <hi>Driades</hi> the watrie</l>
               <l>Nimphs,<note place="margin">The Driades are ſuppoſed to be trees that haue life and ſenſe.</note> of Oliue plants recreat by <hi>Phaebus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Till they be maried.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So beginning ends the report of her fame,</l>
               <l>Whoſe report paſsing any pennes relation,</l>
               <l>Doth entreat her loue, by reinſpiration</l>
               <l>To dull heads yeelding faer eies reflection,</l>
               <l>Still to be preſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
